Guide to the Stanford University, Committee of Educational Inquiry, Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Committee of Educational Inquiry, records
1952-1957
SC0113
Stanford University. Committee of Educational Inquiry.
1 Linear feet
Records include correspondence, minutes, reports, newsletters, and other materials, 1952-57. Nationally, the committees considered three basic topics: aims of liberal arts education, curriculum, and methods of instruction. The Stanford committee addressed the issues of college credit for high school work and the relative merits of the semester and quarter systems. Also included in the collection are minutes, correspondence, and agendas concerning the spring 1957 program of the California Folklore Society, held at Stanford and chaired by Aurelio M. Espinosa, Jr.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Aurelio M. Espinosa, Jr.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
The Stanford Committee of Educational Inquiry was part of a four-year project involving eleven universities, sponsored by the Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching, to enlist faculty aid in the formulation of educational policies. The members of the Stanford committee were Graham P. Du Shane, George S. Parks, William C. Bark, and Aurelio M. Espinosa, Jr.
Description of the Collection
Records include correspondence, minutes, reports, newsletters, and other materials, 1952-1957. Nationally, the committees considered three basic topics: aims of liberal arts education, curriculum, and methods of instruction. The Stanford committee addressed the issues of college credit for high school work and the relative merits of the semester and quarter systems. Also included in the collection are minutes, correspondence, and agendas concerning the spring 1957 program of the California Folklore Society, held at Stanford and chaired by Aurelio M. Espinosa, Jr.
Access Terms
Bark, William Carroll, 1908-; California Folklore Society.; Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching.; Du Shane, Graham Phillips, 1910-; Espinosa, Aurelio Macedonio, 1907-; Parks, George Sutton, 1894-; Stanford University. Committee of Educational Inquiry.; Educational planning.; Universities and colleges--Administration.; Universities and colleges--Planning.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Correspondence
    Correspondence between the Carnegie Foundation, Stanford Committee on Educational Inquiry,(C.E.I.), other C.E.I. committees, and schools in reference to C.E.I. projects.
    - 1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1954 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1955 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - letters addressed to the Stanford C.E.I. committee chairman from schools or individuals requesting a copy of the C.B. I. report on the relative merits of the Semester and Quarter Systems. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - C.E.I. Committees
    newsletters, reading materials, members, conferences, etc., and correspondence between the Carnegie Foundation and C.E.I. committee members.
    - 1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1953 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - minutes, committee member's forms, progress reports, faculty questionnaire, Interim Report on the Semester and Quarter System and budget expenditures of the Stanford C.E.I. Committee, 1952- 1956. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous items concerning the C.E.I. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Reports
    Progress reports, project reports, interim reports on the semester and quarter systems, and an assessment of the C.E.I. project
    - 1952 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1953 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 1954 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 1955 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 1956 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, correspondence, program agendas, etc., concerning the meeting of California Folklore Society chaired by Dr. Aurelio M. Espinoza, Jr., 1957 Spring (Box 2, Folder 6)